Hey there, it's me.
I'm very excited to work with you guys on a new lesson
in the IELTS writing 5.0 to 6.0 course.
Let's make the most of our time together, shall we?
Let's start today's lesson with a question, and please answer honestly.
Raise your hand if you feel dizzy or lightheaded whenever you see
a chart with lots of numbers and images.
After many years of teaching, I understand that many of you often
feel anxious or even panicked when dealing with charts and data, partly
because you lack confidence when choosing information, and partly because you
don't know how to organize or describe them, or where to start.
Everything seems too messy.
But after today's lesson, I believe that you won't have to worry
anymore, because we will work together to analyze charts and learn how
to make a detailed outline.
And we are going to help you with that by looking at
common mistakes that often trap students at band score 5.0, and
what you can do differently to achieve band 6.
Let's look at these four bar charts.
The charts below show the figure for hours per week in the
industrial sector in four European countries in 2002.
Summarize the information by selecting and reporting the main features, and
make comparisons where relevant.
The first mistake is providing no overview.
This is a very important part in your task achievement score.
Many students start describing France's 1-14 hour bar immediately.
To achieve band 6.0, you must provide a summary of the most noticeable features.
So how can we write an overview?
Do you remember the V model?
We learned about it in lesson 1, section 1.
Let me remind you a bit.
It's a two-way thinking method from general to specific and from
specific to general.
Let's use the V model to analyze this question, which involves three steps.
Step 1.
Take an overview of the chart and identify the big three.
Step 2.
Identify the great three.
And step 3.
Go into details and identify the major three.
Alright, according to the V model, in step 1, we need to
take an overview of the chart and identify the big three.
Here, I'm talking about three elements.
The title of the chart, the x-axis or horizontal axis, and
the y-axis or vertical axis.
So we've completed step 1, identify the big three, moving on to step 2.
By looking at the overview of the chart, we will now identify
the great three, corresponding to the three elements, 1.
Subjects of comparison, 2.
Global trends, and 3.
Global features.
For subjects of comparison, we have the following types.
Line graphs include lines.
Bar charts include bars.
These are narrow rectangles and groups of bars.
Tables include rows and columns.
And pie charts, all the sections within the chart.
In these bar charts, the subjects of comparison are bars and groups of bars.
The second element in the great three is global trends.
Trends are the changes over time.
And for charts with trends, this is the most important factor.
So it must be prioritised and clearly defined.
Global trend is the general trend of the graph before we describe
the trend of each line.
I'm sure you still remember.
This is one of the two key components of an overview that
we learned in the previous lesson.
Global trends often include the general trend of all lines, if any.
For example, if all lines in a graph increase, that is also
the global trend of the graph.
And the most significant change.
In this task, your overview should highlight that 36 to 40 hours
was most common for three countries, while France was the exception, with
31 to 35 hours being the peak.
The second common mistake is providing an overview with numbers.
Exact figures like 70% for Denmark belong in the body.
The overview should use general descriptors.
Instead of saying French workers peaked at 40%, say they were most
likely to work between 31 and 35 hours.
Mistake three is describing all data points.
Don't list all eight ranges for France.
Instead, group the low-level data.
In step three, we'll go into details.
To analyse a chart and identify some specific details to include in
this outline, which elements do we need to focus on?
Let's take 30 seconds to think.
Some of you might get lost a bit and don't know where to start.
Here are some suggestions from me.
Please answer the major three questions.
1.
How should the information be divided into two body paragraphs?
2.
Which individual trends and features should be selected?
It means the trends and features of each line.
And 3.
How should we organise this information to describe the chart?
Therefore, we should group minor data to avoid listing everything.
In the France chart, instead of describing eight bars, we describe only
the peak, 31 to 35 hours, and then group the rest.
We can state that about 10% of employees worked below 14
hours over 50 hours and 41 to 45 hours.
This keeps your writing concise and analytical.
Mistake four is a lack of data grouping.
Don't write four separate paragraphs for four countries.
Use the horizontal approach to group subjects with similarities.
Body one should compare France and Denmark, and body two should compare
Sweden and the UK.
We have the following outline for these bar charts.
Mistake five is using the incorrect tense.
This mistake will poorly affect your score on grammar.
Look at the x-axis to identify when.
These charts are from 2002.
All verbs must be in the past tense.
I suggest you write a big word past on your paper to
remind you to use worked, accounted for, or was.
Mistake six is subject-verb disagreement.
When your subject is the proportion of workers, the verb must be
singular because proportion is singular.
For example, write...
Mistake seven is using incorrect prepositions.
Using prepositions accurately in your sentences is very important in grammar
and lexical resources.
For example, using accounted at 70% is a common error.
The correct collocation is accounted for 70%.
Similarly, use stood at or working between 15 and 45 hours.
Next, mistake eight is excessive repetition, which affects your score on
lexical resources.
Do not use workers or common in every sentence.
Vary your vocabulary by using employees, working arrangement, most numerous, or
working time.
In order to avoid these mistakes and improve your lexical resources score,
you need to read a lot and enhance your vocabulary by learning
graph-specific phrases and practicing your paraphrasing skills.
For line graphs and bar charts, you should learn comparative languages,
languages for describing trends and changes over time.
Mistake nine is using incorrect trend verbs.
In our sample task, these charts are static, meaning they don't show changes over time.
Avoid increased or dropped.
Instead, use comparative verbs like was three times the next highest figure
or followed closely by.
Finally, mistake 10 is writing one sentence per data point.
This makes the writing choppy.
Use relative clauses to combine information.
Instead of two sentences, write, In France, people who worked 31 to
35 hours were the most numerous at 40%, followed closely by those
working 36 to 40 hours at 35%.
Now let's look at our sample writing.
Great job so far, everyone.
Today, we learned 10 common mistakes that students might make when describing
line graphs and bar charts.
They are no overview, overview with numbers, describing all data points, lack
of data grouping, incorrect tense, subject-verb disagreement, incorrect
prepositions, excessive repetition, incorrect trend verbs, and one sentence per
data point.
Now let's review through some quick exercises.
Today's lesson has been quite long with a fair amount of information.
Let's take a short break and we'll continue with the analysis and
the horizontal approach in the next lesson.
Have a good one, guys.